<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A single and general voice lifted up like a trumpet, sounding forth the Lords controversie concerning London, with her governors, priests, and citizens that walk in the manners, customs, and way of the heathen, that know not the dreadful God who is Light among them, neither like to retain God ... with somewhat directed to the ear of Thomas Atkin, called alderman of the said city : a reproof to his perverse and ungodly proceedings, message, and two letters ... also a letter from a servant of God in the said prison to Thomas Allen, Mayor of the city ... / by Daniel Baker.</title>
            <author>D. B. (Daniel Baker), fl. 1650-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32851</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12773892</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12773892</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93715</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29619)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93715)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1029:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A single and general voice lifted up like a trumpet, sounding forth the Lords controversie concerning London, with her governors, priests, and citizens that walk in the manners, customs, and way of the heathen, that know not the dreadful God who is Light among them, neither like to retain God ... with somewhat directed to the ear of Thomas Atkin, called alderman of the said city : a reproof to his perverse and ungodly proceedings, message, and two letters ... also a letter from a servant of God in the said prison to Thomas Allen, Mayor of the city ... / by Daniel Baker.</title>
                  <author>D. B. (Daniel Baker), fl. 1650-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: some pages cropped with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93715:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Single and general Voice, Lifted up like a TRUMPET, Sounding forth the Lords Controverſie concerning <hi>London,</hi> with her Governors, Prieſts, and Citizens that walk in the Manners, Cuſtoms, and Way of the Heathen, that know not the dreadful God who is Light among them, neither like to retain God (or that which may be known of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) in their knowledge, like the Sinners of the Gentiles that ſacrifice to Devils, and not unto God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>With ſomewhat directed to the ear of <hi>Thomas Atkin,</hi> called, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the ſaid City; A Reproof to his perverſe and ungodly Proceedings, Meſſage, and Two Letters from his Hand Anſwered, with a lamentable Cry of the Innocent, in and through a Servant of the Church of the Firſt Born in the Inner-Priſon, called, <hi>The Hole,</hi> in the <hi>Poultery Counter</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo a <hi>Letter</hi> from a Servant of <hi>God</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Priſon</hi> to <hi>Thomas Allen</hi> Mayor of the City.</p>
            <p>The ſound may be heard in other parts (and become ſerviceable) in the Nation, though it may be (as it is) Rejected by them that forget Mercy, Truth, Equity, Juſtice and ſound Judgment, the Law and the Prophets, the Lord and his Work, and rather chuſe to ſet their hearts on, and follow after lying Vanities, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their own Mercies [who rebel againſt the Light of Chriſt in the Conſcience of Male and Female] that are ſaying in their hearts as in Ages paſt to the moſt High, (that ſheweth to man what is his thought) <hi>Depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> DANIEL BAKER.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lam. 2.6.</hi>
               </bibl> The Lord hath cauſed the ſolemn Feaſts and Sabbaths to be forgotten in Zion.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 10.</hi>
               </bibl> And I ſaw the Beaſt, and the Kings of the Earth, and their Armies gathered together to make War againſt him who is called Faithful &amp; True.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> neer <hi>Alderſgate</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93715:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A ſingle and general Voice, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>SUrely the Light of Life, even the deſire and health of the Nations is come in the middeſt of a fooliſh people in theſe latter dayes, how many are they that love not their lives unto the death to publiſh and proclaim the joyful ſound hereof to the ends of the Earth, by which the Nations, Kindreds, Tongues, and People are provoked to jealouſie and wrath? but why do the Heathen Rage, and the people imagine vain things, ſeeing he the everlaſting light of the houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> of <hi>Iſraels</hi> life and glory, the ſure Foundation, the Rock, the Hiding-place, the ſtrong Tower, whoſe Name is called the Word of God; by whom the world was made, even he is come in the middſt of us, the true light, that all men through him might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and be ſaved from the wrath to come, by him the light, the Lord of the Sabbath, the ſubſtance, the reſt that ends the ſigns, and lighteth every man that cometh into the world, even he is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever, whoſe day <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>I am,</hi> Lo he is come who is the <hi>(I am)</hi> the Light, the Author of eternal Salvation, the Reſurrection and the Life that is riſen; behold with boldneſs I Teſtifie in his Name that is faithful and true, in the midſt of us, and this is he whoſe righteous Scepter ſhall ſway over the Nations, whoſe dominion ſhall be from Sea to Sea, who ſhall Rule the Nations with his Iron Rod, with the Rod of his mouth will he ſmite the Earth, and with the breath of his Lips will he ſlay the wicked; be wiſe now therefore O ye Kings, be inſtructed O ye Judges of the Earth, ſerve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling, kiſs the Son leſt he be angry and you periſh in the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little, bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</p>
            <p>O <hi>London,</hi> How art thou defiled and poluted and filled with violence, vanity, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, hypocriſie, wickedneſs, and works of darkneſs? Surely thy Governors and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors have greatly erred from the way everlaſting, that ſuch an unwholſome ill ſavour aſcends from thee; thy Paſtors, thy Prieſts and thy Heads have erred and gone aſtray, a whoring, ravening from the Spirit of Truth, &amp; corrupted the way of Holineſs, or that which may be known of God within, and have greatly multiplyed thine iniquities and crying abominations, and ſo have perverted all equity and are eſtranged from the Life of Truth, ſo that the Word of Holineſs is become a Reproach, a taunt and by word in the midſt of thee, thy loud crying ſins are exceedingly increaſed, far exceeding thy Siſter <hi>Sodom</hi> that ſuffered the vengeance of eternal fire, and according to the number of thine Inhabitants, have been thy Dumb IDOLS, or gods that cannot ſave from the power of the SWORD thats to paſſe through the Streets of thy defiled wicked Inhabitants; O! who ſhall bewail thee in the day and hour of thy ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity and diſtreſs, when bitter howling and wayling ſhall be heard, when no eye ſhall pity or weep over thee, when thy Lovers ſhall forſake thee becauſe of the multitude of thy Whordoms greatneſs of pride and haughtineſs, and fornications, and would in no wiſe be cleanſed, purged, or purified by the Word of the higheſt which has been ſounded forth and proclaimed-even in and through thy ſtreets; O <hi>London,</hi> is not thy Land full of Horſes, or is there any end of their wilde Chariots and Idols? Alas, alas, wo and alas for the little ones that lies wounded and oppreſſed under all thy filthy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations, the multitude of thy unclean Beaſts in the midſt of thee are waxed fat and wanton, greedily haſtening and running into the abundance exceſs, and ſo greedily devouring, eating up, and waſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng and ſpoyling the goodl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93715:3"/>ſidue under their feet, ſo that their hearts are waxed groſſe with fatneſs (fitted for the day of ſlaughter) feeding themſelves without fear or amazement over the Worm or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed Seed of the Covenant in the midſt of thee, notwithſtanding the <hi>Lion</hi> hath roared a top of the mountains; O <hi>London, London,</hi> thy ſtink and ill ſavour hath aſcended up into the noſtrils of the moſt holy &amp; higheſt Lord of Lords, &amp; King of Kings, when as thy ſcent or ſmell ſhould have been as <hi>Lebanon,</hi> or as the Ancient Garden of <hi>Eden;</hi> had the precious life of thy long feigned profeſſion of the holy Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles good words freely and clearly aſcended up and ſpread over thy Walls and Towers and Borders, that the Nations round about might have ſcented, taſted, and ſavoured the good and precious fruit of the Life of thy ſeigned Profeſſion, and to have come with joy and rejoycing, ſubmitting and bending unto thee becauſe of thy perfect beauty, had it been brought forth at all in its ſeaſon and comlineſs and bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; as the light that ariſeth in the Eaſt and giveth light unto the ends of the Earth, lo ſuch a thing hath not been brought forth by thy Heads, Paſtors, Prieſts, and Wiſe-men of thy Inhabitants, but out of the North the precious Lilly ſprung up, the ground is bleſſed that bare and brought forth this tender plant, thats never to be forgotten, but to be had in everlaſting remembrance of all that hear the joyful ſound, and come to ſee the glory of the brightneſſe of thy riſing, who ſhall Trumpet forth thy fame to the utmoſt parts of the Earth, and talk of thy mighty power in the Congregation of the righteous.</p>
            <p>O <hi>London, London,</hi> How haſt thou been viſited from on high by the hand of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty in his faithful (though deſpiſed) Meſſengers, that thou might be purged and made clean and healed? Lo the multitude of thy polluted Inhabitants have diſpiſed the day of Healing and of ſmall things, and the Children of Wiſdom [that have been wearied, and as it were ready to faint from time to time under the weight of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy pollutions and crying abominations, and] have truly bewailed and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented thy eſtate; but how have they been eſteemed in thine Adulterous eyes as ſounding Braſs, as ſigns and wonders, the off ſcouring of the World, or as the Wind, thou haſt not known whence they come, neither whether they go</p>
            <p>O <hi>London,</hi> Thy defiled Garments, thy Heads, thy Prieſts, thy Paſtors, Profeſſors, and Prophane in thee, thy Judgment Seats, thy Courts, thy Palaces, with them that that handle the Law, thy Idols Temples, loe even thy ſtreets in theſe latter dayes are ſtained with the blood of the Innocent; O <hi>England, England,</hi> what haſt thou done or brought forth? how canſt thou like an impudent Harlot or murtherer, plead before the glorious Throne of the Lord God of Judgement (and of the Lamb the Son of the higheſt) and ſay not guilty, or I am innocent.</p>
            <p>O <hi>London,</hi> (Remember <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) its yet but a very little while, &amp; thy day is paſſed over thy head, ſome of thy Mourners have already ſeen, and yet behold the Lillies co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the mountains, the good watchmen of the City (<hi>Zion</hi> where the Sabbaths which thou haſt prophaned and polluted, are forgotten) waite for the gathering and healing of the remaining little ones that are defiled, wounded, and polluted even in thee.</p>
            <p>O <hi>London,</hi> Proclaim ye this among the Gentiles, prepare War, wake up the mighty men, all the men of War, let them come up, beat your Plow ſhares into Swords, and your Pruning-Hooks into Spears, Let the Weak ſay I am ſtrong.</p>
            <p>Aſſemble your ſelves and come, all ye Heathen, aſſemble your ſelves-together round about thither, cauſe thy mighty ones to come down O Lord, let the Heathen be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked and come up to the valley of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> for there will I ſit to Judge the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then round about, put ye in the Sickle for the Harveſt is ripe; Come get ye down, for the Preſs is full, the Fats over flow, for their wickedneſs is great, See <hi>Joel</hi> the third.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93715:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>O ye heads and polluted Inhabitants of <hi>London</hi> that call the Scripture your rule, read and behold your State, ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. and when the Lord ſaw it, he abhorred them becauſe of the provoking of his Sons and of his Daughters, and he ſaid, <hi>I will hide my face from them, I will ſee what their end ſhall be, for they are a very froward gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, children in whom is no faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They have moved me to jealouſie with that which is not God (they provoked him to jealouſie with ſtrange gods) they have provoked me to anger with their vanities, and I will move them to jealouſie with thoſe which are not a people, I will provoke them to anger with a fooliſh Nation, for a fire is kindled in mine anger, and ſhall burn unto the loweſt hell, and ſhall conſume the earth with her increaſe, and ſet on fire the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the mountains; I will heap miſchiefs upon them, I will ſpend mine arrows upon them, they ſhall be burnt with hunger, and devoured with burning heat, and with bitter deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as it hath been the manner and antient cuſtome of the Mayors, Aldermen, Governours, Citizens, and inhabitants of the City of London; the day when their chief Governour is ſworn to do juſtice, at ſuch ſeaſons, great ſhews, and wicked dark vile inventions is acted and brought forth in and through the open ſtreets and River of the City, becauſe of which exceeding great multitudes of people aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and gather together from divers parts in the vanitie of their vaine minds, which are led captive to many and divers hurtful luſts, that war againſt their ſouls at ſuch ſeaſons; by which the Creatures are waſted, conſumed, devoured and deſtroyed, (without the fear and wiſdom of God) by high and low, rich and poor, young and old, bond and free, for which end they were not created, and the everlaſting God hereby is greatly provoked, and highly diſhonoured, though <hi>Thomas Atkin</hi> attribute it to the honour and reſpect of the Magiſtrates; But <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> the good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates was not found walking in theſe or ſuch like wayes; and the perſons of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures hurt, and ſometime in great jeopardy to the loſs of life by land and water, and from time to time, the Lord God and his ſpirit hath been grieved, oppreſſed and vexed with theſe vain filthy abhominations of the heathen, and Prieſts, Rulers and people have been and are in a high degree guilty of all the hurt and waſte of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo much to the provoking and diſhonour of the Almighty Lord and everlaſting God of Truth, yea and my ſpirit within me hath been often preſſed down and griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe of the weight of the crying abhominations of Prieſts, Rulers and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are called Chriſtians, but are not profirted at all by them the hired Prieſts that teach for filthy lucre, their own way, their gain from their Quarters, like greedy dogs that can never have enough, and are ſo plentifully bringing forth the fruits and works of darkneſſe, walking in the manners of the Gentiles; and way of the Heathen, and pleading for their dumb Idols; wherefore I was not onely moved to write to the two Mayors, namely <hi>John Ireten</hi> and <hi>Thomas Allen,</hi> to lay before them and to ſtop them and their ſubjects of their folly and wicked vanity (but they would not receive warning) as may appear by a paper afterwards publiſhed and Tituled <hi>A certain Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a naked Heart.</hi> But the twenty ninth of the eighth moneth, on which their Heatheniſh Ancient Idolatrous cuſtoms and dark inventions was ſo highly ſet up and exalted, and carried th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ugh the open ſtreets, at which many thouſands of people gazed, before which time I ſpake a few words of Truth and ſoberneſſe which the Lord put into my heart to ſome of the Aldermen, as the horſes and their Riders paſſed in at the Mayors gate; ſaying, The Lord God will ſtain the pride and glory of all fleſh, the Lord God will ſtain the pride of all glory as in the dayes of old; the Lord will ſmite the great men of the earth with aſtoniſhment of heart, who forget Juſtice and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Lord God hath a controverſie with all that forget the Lord and his work.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:93715:4"/>
            <p>The Lord will be avenged on the great men of the earth that deſtroy and devour the Creatures and the Creation upon their ungodly luſts, and forget to do Juſtice and Judgement, for which ſayings, I was not onely buffeted and abuſed at the Mayors gate by the brutiſh people, but violently dragged &amp; carried away by Porters, and thrown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Poultry Counter</hi> by <hi>Thomas Atkins</hi> his unreaſonable will without a <hi>Mittimus;</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">But Noble <hi>Feſtus,</hi> whom the Profeſſors, Prieſts and praphane call Heathen could not do ſo, <hi>Act. 25.27</hi>
               </note> throw him in ſaid the Officer, and let him lie like a Rogue, and afterward a <hi>Mittimus</hi> was ſent though dated the ſame day; The Coppy is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>LONDON, ſſ.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THeſe are in the Name of the Keepers of the Liberty of Englamd by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Parliament, to require to detain and ſafely keep in your cuſtody the Body of <hi>Daniel Baker,</hi> until he find good ſecurity to appear at the next Seſſions of peace in LONDON, and in the mean time to be of the good behaviour; oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned a great tumult of people to be gathered together in the Streets, to the the great diſquiet of the City, and diſturbance of the publick peace, and this ſhall be your Warrant.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated <date>the twenty ninth day of Octo. <hi>1659.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>to the keeper of the <hi>Poultry Counter.</hi>
                  </trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thomas Atkin.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as I ſhould have been called to appear at the next Seſſions of peace in London, according to equity and the words in the Mittimus alſo; but equity, juſtice &amp; judgement was paſt by and forgotten, and I was not called, but kept a cloſe Priſoner in a ſtinking hole of the Priſon ſome weeks after, and I had not onely laid before the Jay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor the unjuſtneſſe of my Sufferings, but that it was more then he or the unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Juſtice, according to the Law of the Nation could anſwer what they had done, and the ſame day as I underſtand, the Jaylor informed the Juſtice (concerning the Matter) who ſent a private Meſſenger to have me come at his will, which caſt me into priſon openly, and to have ſet me free ſecretly, but at that ſeaſon I had not free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the Lord that gave me to ſee the wicked unreaſonableneſſe of their dealings with me, and therefore had more Chriſtian boldneſſe to write to him (the Coppy of the Letter is thus written.)</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>This body in which I am with every Member of it is the Lords, and ſo was and is the teſtimony of Gods truth, whoſe words I ſpoke forth (in obedience to his moſt Pure Spirit (in my heart) that reproves the World for ſin; the twenty ninth day of the eighth moneth, and ſeventh or laſt day of the week, when the great, wiſe and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Men and inhabitants of the Earth [and the wiſdom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> honour) that is from beneath is earthly, ſenſual and devilliſh] aſſembled together at <hi>Thomas Allens</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Mayors houſe, and from thence thou with them accompanied, and tollerated in a high degree the wicked inventions, and idolatrous heatheniſh cuſtoms of the men of ſin, kept up and tollerated and highly exalted in courſe and time with vain fleſhly glory by ſuch that ſhould be more wiſe, who are called Chriſtians, Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Members of Churches, Governours, Mayors and Aldermen, them to be found
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93715:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Acting and giving up their ſtrength, means and precious time to lying vanities, rather then to be good, ſound, ſober examples to all both young and old, and for them to be found acting and exerciſeing themſelves in ſuch Heatheniſh abhominations, and wicked vain cuſtoms of the World that lyeth in wickedneſſe, to be laught at by fools and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, though poor wiſe men lament over and pitty you by reproving (with their life) thoſe evils you are found in, to the end that you might not die in your ſins, which grives and wounds the juſt principle of God in your ſelves and others, which Teſtimony is one with that which is true that condems the unjuſt.</p>
                  <p>But Friend, was not this Body with the true Teſtimony from the Mayors gate [by thy will caſt into a filthy noyſome Priſon] from which place by violence with Porters and others carried through the open ſtreets in the ſight of many hundreds of people, as if I had been ſuch a vile perſon or tranſgreſſor not worthy to live, and the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude might ſo judge of me, ſeeing me thus openly carried and dragged, as or far worſe then many Malefactors or murtherers have been.</p>
                  <p>And what, haſt thou forgot to do Juſtice and Judgement, and doſt thou ſend for me ſecretly? for as much as the Law is open, and if I have committed any thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of death or bonds, Lo here is a body prepared to ſuffer, and according to the <hi>Mittimus</hi> thou ſent (after I was thus thrown into a noyſome hole of a Priſon by thy will, and under thy hand in writing) I ſhould have appeared at the laſt Seſſions of Peace (ſo called) in <hi>London,</hi> but I was not called according to the Tennour of the <hi>Mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> and ſo thou haſt greatly erred, and art found a tranſgreſſor thy ſelf, and the Lords faithful witneſſe in thy Conſcience will judge thee for it, and my words I ſpake as the Lord moved me at the Mayors gate is already fulfilled upon thy head, where it will ſtaud aright; Lo thou haſt forgot to do juſtice and judgement, if thou had not, thou would have (without delay) cauſed me to have appeared at the Judgement Seat, there to be Tryed openly, as I was caſt into Priſon openly, and if I had ſpoke or done any thing worthy of Death or of Bonds, the Law was open, and thou ought equally and openly to have executed true Juſtice and Judgement, and to have laid the ſword up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head of the tranſgreſſor, and ſo to have been a terror to the evil doer.</p>
                  <p>Lo the Sword is to be laid upon thy Head O Man, who haſt forgot equity, and loſt pure Reaſon, Juſtice and Judgement, and thrown the Teſtimony of Truth into Priſon ſo openly; and what, doſt thou fend privately to have this Body which is the Lords, to do his will and not mine own, neither mans will that caſt me in,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From the hole in the inner Priſon in the <hi>Poultry Counter,</hi> 
                        <date>the 15 of the 9 mo. 1659.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Who am the Lords Priſoner for the Teſtimony of a pure Conſcience, for the Elects ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Seeds ſake; A Friend to thy Soul, called,</hi> Daniel Baker,</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The above written Letter was delivered to <hi>Thomas Atkin</hi> his hand, and the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brought me tidings that he read it, and when he had done tore it to pieces and laught, ill becoming his age, gray hairs and place, who after ſome dayes ſent me a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Night when it was dark, a figure of his unfruitful works, who hates to be reformed, and to the end that others may beware and learn wiſdome, which many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject whoſe deeds are with Gods fear and Wiſdom to be brought to the Light which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually tryeth all things, and accordingly reproves and condemneth, or approveth and juſtifieth, I ſay according to the faithful and true witneſſe in the Conſcience of Male and Female, ſo ſhall every ones deeds done in the body be condemned or juſtified, as is the ground and nature by which they are conceived and brought forth, theſe are the true ſayings of the ſure word of propheſie that gave forth the Scriptures of Truth, he that can believe and receive it without offence, let him.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93715:5"/>
                  <head>The Coppy of <hi>Thomas Atkin</hi> his Letter is as followeth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DAniel Baker,</hi> I ſaw you at my Lord Mayors gate upon the twenty ninth day of October laſt, being the firſt day when he came from Weſtminſter, you were in a wild poſture, more like a mad man then a ſober perſon, you were then adviſed to return to your houſe, but you ſtill continued there in drawing a great concourſe of people about you, to the great diſturbance of the peace of this City, drawing Cut-purſes and Pick-pokets about you, a fit time for ſuch perſons to commit Robbery; you were then deſervedly carried to the Counter by force by Porters as I am informed, who were paid for their pains taken about you, if you had gone willingly, you ſhould not have been drag'd thither; A Friend of yours deſired me to diſcharge you, to that end I ſent for you to come unto me, intending to have admoniſhed you to make no ſuch diſturbance for the future, and then to have diſcharged you, but you writ me a Letter, and ſent me word by your Keeper, that you would be dragged out as you were carried in <hi>(this is falſe)</hi> and if that be your mind, when you deſire your Liberty, get a keeper to bring you to me, and I ſhall give a diſcharge, in the mean time if you want any fitting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation in the Counter, it is your own fault, I pitty your condition, the Lord open your eyes, and ſo I Reſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Leaden-hall ſtreet</hi> London <date>
                           <hi>the 18 of</hi> Nov. <hi>1659.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your well-wiſhing Friend, <hi>THOMAS ATKIN</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Friend, I have received thy Letter, and I did not tear it to pieces after I read it as thou didſt mine. But how is it thou art ſo dark and blind, though thou ſaw me at thy Lord Mayors gate, Why could not thou ſee to do juſtice, and relieve the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within and without, and ceaſe from peviſhneſſe and perverſneſſe, madneſſe and folly? for it is high time for thee to learn moderation and ſobriety, and ceaſe from falſe accuſing the Lords Servant, whom thou ſay appeared more like a mad man (then a ſober perſon) in a wilde poſture; know thou that the Servant is not above his Lord, of whom ſuch as crucified him ſaid he is mad and hath a Devil, and if they called the Maſter of the houſe <hi>Belzebub,</hi> how much more them of his houſhold; and however I appeared to thee know it was the Lords Truth and Teſtimony I declared that ſeaſon againſt your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations, I ſpake the words of Truth and ſobernes as any moderate men may read in a Book Tituled, <hi>A certain Warning,</hi> which is fulfilling, and is to be fulfilled upon the heads of ſuch as are with thee in thy Life and Nature.</p>
            <p>Thou ſay I was adviſed that day to return to my houſe; I ſay it becomes not a Ruler to hearken to, or to ſpeak a lie, which I turn back upon thy head, for I heard none ſpeak ſuch words to me; and foraſmuch as thou ſay, I continued there drawing a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of people about me, drawing Cut-purſes and Pick-pockets about me, and thou ſay a fit time for ſuch perſons to commit a robbery, then I ſay ſuch vile tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors are beholding to the early Rulers that occaſion ſo fit opportunities ſo frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, more eſpecially in the wicked City <hi>London,</hi> of all Cities and Towns throughout the Nations; and I ſay, how is it that thou art ſo dark and ſottiſh, that thou can lay ſuch a charge upon me, as the cauſe of ſuch tranſgreſſors or concourſe of people gathering together. Behold I tell thee, this filth is not to lie upon the head of the Innocent, but to be turned back upon the head of the tranſgreſſer from whence it came; and art not thou together with many more of the earthly Rulers, Mayor, Aldermen and Citizens of this wicked City inexcuſeable herein, let the Lords witneſſe in all ſober peoples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences judge of this matter.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93715:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And if ſuch a ſmall number of perſons gathered together at the <hi>Mayors</hi> gate, were a fit time for Cut-purſes and Pick-pockets to commit robbery, I query how fit and large opportunities have they ſo frequently given them by the Rulers of the earth which forget Juſtice and Judgement, [as thou have done] and to relief the oppreſſed, and rather exalt folly and vanity, and heatheniſh cuſtomes which captivates the minds of people out of Gods fear at ſuch ſeaſons, when the Mayor Aldermen and great Earthly wiſe men that have loſt the key of knowledge, the oppreſſing Lawyers and Rabbies, with their folly and vanity and heatheniſh cuſtoms and idolatrous abominations, with them is carried through the open ſtreets of the wicked City, when ſo many thouſands of people are gathered together [to ſee the Beaſt that carries the Whore ariſe out of the troubled Sea] and to behold your vanitie, and wicked folly, and dark inventions, and vain glory and exceſſe, which you waſt and conſume upon your luſts which war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſouls, when ſo many poor widdows and fatherleſſe, halt, blind and lame creeples ſo plentifully, lye crying and lamenting up and down your ſtreets, and Maſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe doors, and corners of Allies for want of bread, food and rayment, and honeſt employments to be ſet at, work at them that can work; The Lord God will aſſuredly account with you for theſe things, and for his Creatures which you ſo greedily waſte and conſume upon your ungodly luſts; and thou ſay I was deſervedly carried to the Counter by force by Porters, and what is my crime thou charge me with, both in the Mittimus and thy Letter to me? <hi>viz.</hi> I occaſioned a great Tumult of people to be gathered together, drawing a great concourſe of people, of Cut-purſes and Pick-pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets about you [ſay thou to me;] But heark Friend, haſt thou a Law for ſuch Crimes, or is this of thy own making? Now if there be ſuch a Law in force, to be equally mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred or executed upon all without reſpect of perſons (which is but reaſonable, and all Laws ſhould be grounded upon pure Reaſon) that occaſion great Tumults of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be gathered together, amongſt whom doubtleſſe may be tranſgreſſors of all ſorts, ſuch as the Prieſts keep ever learning what to ſay, but do not, (like themſelves) Then what will become of all the earthly wiſe men of <hi>London,</hi> what, muſt they not all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly be carried to priſon? I may appeal to the chief Authority in the Nation, and if the Lords faithful and true witneſſe in their Conſciences will condemne me, Lo I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; but who occaſioned any, or the greateſt tumult or coucourſe of people to gather together, whether the Rulers and wiſe men of <hi>London,</hi> in exalting their folly, vanity and vain glory (which the everlaſting God will ſtain and bring to contempt) or I that in the fear and power of the Lord, ſpeak a few words of Truth and Soberneſſe, a Teſtimony againſt your Heatheniſh Cuſtoms and wicked actions, which if <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> were here to behold you, no doubt but they would abhor, and deteſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie you and your vain Religion, rather then to be won to the faith of Gods Elect, by ſuch ſtinking and unſavoury examples, to the ſhame of your dark teachers and bruitiſh paſtors And the Lord is a pleading with the Inhabitants of the Earth, becauſe of their mighty ſins, and whoriſh, hypocritical coverings, and inventions of the Whore, of the Beaſt, and of the man of Sin, together with the Witchcraft and Sorceries of the Mother of Harlots, the well-favoured Harlot, that hath ſo beſotted and made the Kings and Rulers of the Earth, even of all Nations of the Earth drunk with the Wine of her Fornication; all Tables are full of Vomit, wo to the Inhabitants of the Earth.</p>
            <p>Moreover thou ſay, if I had gone willingly, I had not been dragged, (to Priſon) what, is thy Conſcience ſeared? art thou altogether impenitent O man? and thou I perceive doſt rather countenance and ſtrengthen the hands of evil doers, that offer and do violence in a bruitiſh manner, by buffeting and dragging the guiltleſſe and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to Priſon, to which place I was forced, I knowing aſſuredly by the Teſtimony
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93715:6"/>of the Lord God within me, that I was innocent in his ſight, and a priſon I deſerved not, (and had thou been a man of God, thou might have ſavoured and ſeen ſo much alſo) and therefore not willing to go or ſubject to the corrupt will of vain man, but was therefore as a Sheep to the ſlaugter drove, dragged and carried where I ſhould not have been, and this in the day when the Lords hand viſits (from which thou can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fly nor hide) will lie heavy upon thy conſcience, in the mean time I leave it to the witneſs in thee.</p>
            <p>Again thou ſpeaks in thy Letter, thou ſent for me to admoniſh me, but thou being found a tranſgreſſor thy ſelf, art not fit to admoniſh another, but to be threſhed and admoniſhed thy ſelf; and then to have diſcharged me, thou ſay (ſecretly) when as I was ſo openly dragged (as a great offender) to Priſon, and thou may know that my words are fulfilled upon thy head, <hi>viz.</hi> thou haſt forgot to do Juſtice and Judgement, in as much as thou ſent not for me before the Judgement Seat, where I ought to be tryed openly as I was caſt into Priſon openly, and if I am found a Tranſgreſſor of any Law either of God or man, Lo I refuſe not to ſuffer or to die.</p>
            <p>And moreover thou ſaid thus, you writ me a Letter, and ſent me word by your Keeper, that you would be dragged out as you were dragged in.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, this is falſe, I ſaid not ſo, but I told thy meſſenger and the Keeper, if thou ſent for me as I was caſt into Priſon, that I was in their hands, they may do as they were commanded, but know thou that he that neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps is my keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, though this veſſel, ſuffer under thy corrupt will, and I was not willing to be dragged to Priſon, neither to be dragged out, and thou did write me word, ſaying, <hi>if that be your mind, when you deſire your liberty, get a Keeper to bring you to me, and I ſhall give you a diſcharge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know thou that my mind is become ſubject to the Higher Power, (the light) that is higher then the power of darkneſſe, and behold I demand my liberty with boldneſs, as my proper right, (for I have deſerved no bonds, for the pretious truth of God is on my ſide) as a Friend and Servant of the Lord, and ſo a true Chriſtian; and as I am a free-born Engliſh-man in this land of my nativity, and as I have ſerved my gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and moreover dearly purchaſed by the ſhedding of my blood, and ſhattering of my bones, not onely in my own behalf, as <hi>I</hi> am a Chriſtian, an Engliſh-man, a Free-born Member of this Nation; but in the behalf of all the Free-born In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Land, and thou alſo haſt a ſhare in what <hi>I</hi> and many more have jeoparded our Lives and Eſtates to purchaſe, and what art thou found without Natural affection, who alſo ſay (after thou have thus cruelly executed thy enmity againſt me by caſting me into priſon) if you want any thing, it is your own fault, and ſay thus, <hi>I pitty your condition, the Lord open your eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I know the Lord heareth not Sinners, he who was born blind and had his eyes opened by the Light Chriſt, ſaid ſuch words, and how doſt thou pitty me, if I have of my own I need not want, or it is my own fault thou ſay, then it is like I may pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for all thy pitty, and the tender mercies of the wicked is cruelty, ſaith the wiſe man, but know thou that if my outward man periſh in this noyſome hole of a priſon, that my blood will lie heavy upon thy conſcience more eſpecially, and many more may feel the weight of it alſo, if ſo, and the Lord whom I ſerve, I know then will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it at thy hand; therefore ſee thou to it, for ſo far have I cleared my Conſcience, and I can truly ſay, I reſt in peace, but <hi>I</hi> know thou ſpake not truth, in ſaying ſo in thy Letter, for the Lords Eternal and Faithful witneſſe in thy Conſcience ſpeaks not peace to thee, and ſo thou cannot reſt, and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>the wicked are like the troubled Sea, that cannot reſt, but caſt or foam up mire and dirt,</hi> and ſober people may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93715:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>favour the dirty ſtuff and corrupt fruit thou bears and brings forth; therefore it is needful thou repent of this thy wickedneſſe, and bring forth fruits meet for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, leaſt thou die in thy ſins, and if they were to depart into everlaſting flames or unquenchable fire that viſited not Chriſts little ones, ſick and in priſon; what thinks thou will be their portion, that not onely caſt them in, but ſpeaks all manner of evil againſt them? let this remain with thee and many more of thy brethren, the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Rulers of <hi>England;</hi> the Lord lay it not to the charge of them who ſimply know not what they do, Father forgive them.</p>
            <p>And how can you be clear, and not guilty of all the Robberies, (committed at ſuch a fit time as <hi>Thomas Atkin</hi> calls it) hurt to the Creatures, and of waſting and devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Creatures and the Creation thus upon your ungodly luſts time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time, by which you tempt and and provoke the eternal Spirit of the Lord God to ſmite you, and to give you up to the deceit and exceſſe of your own hearts luſts.</p>
            <p>May not the Cut-purſes, Pick-pokets and evil doers, ſay and rejoyce in the ſtrength of their wicked hearts, with ſuch gladneſſe that they have ſuch fit opportunitiies, ſo frequently given them by the Governours, Magiſtrates, and earthly great men that ſhould be more wiſe, and be good, ſober, ſound, ſavoury examples to all, and a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to evil doers; and can you I ſay be clear of the ſame crimes that you will judge and condemn ſuch vile Tranſgreſſors for; be wiſe therefore and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and remove the cauſe of ſuch fit opportunities or times, as <hi>Thomas Atkins</hi> calls them.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as people that ſuffer in any degree at ſuch ſeaſons may ſay, if the Rulers and Magiſtrates did ceaſe to proceed in their heatheniſh Idolatrous Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and vain glory, by which the Lord God is ſo highly diſhonoured, tempted and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked from time to time, (by which alſo many thouſands of people gather together to gaze at folly and wickedneſſe, and run greedily into the exceſſe, pride, vanity, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and hurtful luſts of the fleſh, that war againſt the Lambs Spirit, and neglect their honeſt imployments, we ſhould not thus ſuffer in any degree, when the fit time as thou calls it, or I ſay rather wicked and vain opportunities be removed and taken away.</p>
            <p>And this I may ſay to clear my Conſcience on the Lords behalf, and I know it of a truth, had not the Spirit of the moſt high been oppreſt, vexed and grieved with the long continuance of your wicked heatheniſh actions, doubtleſſe the Lord had not at any time ſent any of his Meſſengers to teſtifie againſt and reprove you, and to lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you your mighty ſins, and to cry aloud, and lift up their voices like Trumpets, though they be looked upon or eſteemed by the unwiſe, as mad men, contrary to all men, for reproving you for your folly, vanity and wickedneſſe, did it not thus abound in all Streets through the Nation, as the upright in heart feel ſomething of the weight of your wickedneſſe and great abominations, and the everlaſting God will plead with his Righteous Judgement with you, for a ſword is to paſſe through your Land, Oh ye ſtiff-necked Generation, for theſe things, and except you repent and depart from evil by the fear of the Lord, which is the beginning of Wiſdome, the Light of the World, whoſe light is in every one of your Conſciences, and with it you bring forth fruit meet for repentance unto life, as ſure as the Lord God hath given you breath, you ſhall die in your ſins, and this is love to thy ſoul, among the reſt that lyeth under the bondage of corruption.</p>
            <p>What I have ſuffered ſince I came into Priſon is unexpreſſible becauſe of ſin, ſinful men, ungodlineſſe, blaſphemy and prophaneneſſe that abounds, which with my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious life from time to time, I have Teſtified againſt, becauſe of which I have endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93715:7"/>the Contradictions of ungodly ſinners day by day, and as truly as the Soul of righteous <hi>Lot</hi> was vexed from day to day with the filthy Converſation of the wicked <hi>Sodomites,</hi> ſo certainly have I witneſſed the like Condition in this noyſom Priſon, where wickedneſſe and ungodlineſſe daily abounds [and where is there a Priſon in this Nation that is not as it were a Nurſery for all manner of abominations, and the Rulers ought to ſee to it that they be not ſo, elſe will it not lie upon their heads, and is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced and upheld by the Keepers alſo, that ſhould be, as every Magiſtrate ought to be, a juſt man of Truth, hating Covetouſneſs and to deſpiſe and ſhake their hand at the gain of Oppreſſion, and ſo to Rule over and be a good example, a terror to evil-doers, that ſuch may go out with a reformed life, rather better then worſe then when they came in; but contrariwiſe the chief Goaler or Keeper hath gone about and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to limit the Spirit of the Lord; Behold, to his everlaſting praiſe I teſtifie that I have gladly received that into my heart to Rule me, and hath the preheminence, even the Spirit of Truth, the Light that reproves the world for ſin, and with my life in my hand have I reproved and teſtified againſt wickedneſs and ungodlineſs, blaſphemy, and the like evils that abound in this Priſon, for which the Keeper <hi>Humphry Gifford</hi> (a Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles good words) hath cauſed men to draw me away and caſt me into a place where the filth of the priſoners run almoſt round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me, and this is of truth that <hi>I</hi> write, and at that ſeaſon my Teſtimony <hi>I</hi> declared and laid it upon his head, who Commanded me to be taken away becauſe <hi>I</hi> Reproved blaſphemy and ungodlineſs, he ſaid, <hi>I ſpake too loud,</hi> although unclean and ungodly Songs and wicked Revellings, as it were, made the houſe ring again imediately after, as at other ſeaſons; and <hi>Humphry Gifford</hi> will remember this when the hand of the Lord viſits for all the deeds done in the body; and foraſmuch as he who ſhould have been a terror to evil doers, ſtrengthened their hands by commanding violence to be done to me that Reproved ſin and ungodlineſs with my life, the Lord is witneſs, and ſundry men that are more ſober then the reſt, can alſo bear Record.</p>
            <p>And moreover, every firſt day of the Week, ſince I have been in Bonds, have the Priſoners done violence to me and my Friend <hi>Humphry Bach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and forced and carried us into the <hi>Hole</hi> of the <hi>Priſon,</hi> and Locked us up by the Keepers Order, becauſe we could not for Conſcience ſake, but did refuſe to enter into Covenant with them, <hi>viz.</hi> to be ſilent (and ſo limit the Spirit of the Lord, whoſe peculiar right only is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Tongue and every Member of our body at his good will in us to work) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſuch a thing be not demanded of any other of the Priſoners; and although we have been there while they have been at part of their Worſhip, and ſpake never a word, yet have they abuſed, and then done violence and taken me up and carried me into the <hi>Hole</hi> and locked me up, and one Friend thruſt out of Door by one <hi>Parrat</hi> a Turn-key, with ſuch violence as if he would have broke her neck; and ſometime after I asked him, ſaying, <hi>How if thou hadſt broke her neck? Then I ſhould be hanged for it,</hi> ſaid he; And let the Magiſtrates conſider, Whether ſuch perſons be fit to have any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or at leaſt to ſerve ſober perſons, and the Prieſts that profeſſe themſelves Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt beholding ſuch Cruelties, and not a mouth open to reprove them that do violence, (and one Prieſt, a priſoner for Debt, ſaid in the hearing of many Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; <hi>There was no way to Diſpute with us but with blows.</hi> Let the ſober mind weigh and judge of theſe things) But ſometime ſtanding behind the Door like a Thief and would not come in, as if he were aſhamed to tell his Dream, or ſtudied ſtuffe, or Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his own brain, or to deliver his meſſage, till we have been thus taken and carried violently out of his ſight as Sheep to the ſlaughter, and caſt into the <hi>Hole</hi> of the priſon, and notwithſtanding that <hi>Humphry Gifford,</hi> chief Goaler, had Covenanted with the Hired Prieſt, (and <hi>Judas Iſcariot</hi> the Traytor went from the light, the unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Prieſt, to the changeable Prieſts, and Covenanted with them to betray and inſnare
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93715:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Innocent) that we ſhould hear the Prieſt one time to try us; yet he ſaw and alſo confeſt to a Friend, That the Prieſt his heart failed him ſo that he could not, or dare not come in, until we were carried away and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cked up in the <hi>Hole</hi> (as at other times) but had he been a Miniſter of Chriſt he would not have been afraid or aſhamed, neither would his heart have failed him, or feared the face of any man, but would with boldneſs without guilt upon the Conſcience, which cauſeth the heart to fail, and bringeth ſhame, to have anſwered a ſober queſtion, which by one of them was denyed, but would, if a Miniſter of Chriſt, or Spirit of Life, with all readineſs of mind count it all joy to Convince the gain ſayers by ſound Doctrine; and if we were in Errors, as we are falſly accuſed, the Lord is witneſſe he ought to do ſo, and bring his deeds to the light that they may manifeſtly appear before all that they are unreproveable, wrought in God, and if ſuch hired Prieſts be Miniſters of Chriſt or of the Spirit of Life, let ſuch as fear and deſire to fear the God of truth judge; And let this be a Warning to <hi>Humphry Gifford,</hi> or any that ſees the deceit of the Hirelings, (and I told one of them in the priſon before he did fly, that he would make himſelf manifeſt to the people; and immediately he did fly, becauſe he was a Hireling, and ſo the Scripture is fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon his head) leſt ſuch partake with them in their plagues; for behold the Lords hand is lifted up againſt the hired Prieſts and bruitiſh Paſtors of <hi>England</hi> that ſteal the Prophets good words that were ſpoke freely forth, and boaſt in other mens lines made ready to their hand, which they make a Trade on through Covetous practiſes, beguil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unſtable Souls, and keep them ever learning what to ſay, but like themſelves do not.</p>
            <p>And the Cry that hath often paſſed through me, ſince I have been a Priſoner here, againſt the abominations in this priſon, has been, O the Ungodlineſs, O the Oathes, O the Blaſphemy, O the Curſed Speaking, O the ungodly Unclean Songs of the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, O the Deceit of the Prieſts, O the ungodly hard Speeches, O the Exceſs, O the Revellings, O the want of the poorer ſort. O the unreaſonableneſs of men harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Gods fear, O the cruel Mockings &amp; Revilings from ſinful men, O the Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, O the Extortion, O the wicked Cuſtoms; O let this enter into thy heart, O many, &amp; lie even upon thine &amp; the Keepers head; who as for thy part, when I ſent a Letter to thee in love to thy Soul, thou tore it to pieces and laughed, as I hear, not becoming thy Age, and gray Hairs, and place; but thou haſt more need to weep and howl for the miſery that is comming on thee becauſe of thy mighty crying ſins.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Humphry Gifford,</hi> hath often by words our of thine own mouth rejected the Lords Teſtimony to my face from time to time, and this is truth whether thou canſt believe me or nay, it will ſtand upon thy head, if happily thou find a place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance unto life, the Lord lay not theſe things to your Charge; however ſo far have I cleared my Conſcience, and my Peace in which I reſt no man can take from me;</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Hole</hi> in the Inner-Priſon in the <hi>Counter,</hi> the 19 of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th.</hi> Month, and 7 or laſt day of the week, and of the year according to the Worlds account, 1659.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who am a Friend to the whole Creation (that groans for Deliverance, and lieth under the bondage of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and with that which judgeth the evil-doer, but juſtifieth and giveth life to him whoſe deeds are wrought in God, in Truth, in Righteouſneſs.</hi> Daniel Baker.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93715:8"/>
            <p>The Original of this in Writing was delivered into the hand of <hi>Thomas Atkin,</hi> by a Friend of Gods Truth, <hi>Elizabeth harris,</hi> who with much tenderneſs and bowels of Compaſsion tendered it to him, and ſpake ſome good wholſome words, being grieved to ſee the injuſtice of ſuch men as he, who inſtead of being aſhamed of his perverſneſs, and diſowning of his injuſtice and unequal proceeding againſt the Innocent, perſiſted and reiected wholſome Counſel, and ſpake forth a moſt wicked Lye, ſaying, That <hi>I had gathered all the Pick-pockets, Rogues and Whores in</hi> London <hi>about me, and that I was like to lie in Priſon till I was dragged out;</hi> and Reviled the ſober Meſſenger, ſaying to ſome that ſtood by, <hi>You may know that ſhe is a Quaker by her Language;</hi> which I ſay is pure and true.</p>
            <p>Now I leave this to the witneſs in all ſober peoples Conſciences to judge whether ſuch a man befit to Rule over men, It's like I might be about an hour and half at the Mayors Gate, and it would be much if all the pick-pockets, and all the Whores, and all the Rogues in <hi>London</hi> ſhould be gathered together in ſo little time, except they had been ſummoned before-hand; but I deny ſuch unclean vile Tranſgreſſors with my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Life the Lord is witneſſe; and ſeeing if <hi>Thomas Atlin</hi> knew ſo well of ſo many Cut-purſes, pick-pockets, Whores and Rogues were gathered together, I ſay it had been a fitter time for him, and many more of his Brethren, to have laid the Sword up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch vile Tranſgreſſors, and not to have let them gone free and condemne the guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by throwing Truths teſtimony into priſon within and without; But I have ſpoke enough, and my Reward is with the Lord, though <hi>Thomas Atkin</hi> have unwiſely rejected his Teſtimony with many more, who greedily are haſtening farther under the vail of thick darkneſs, therefore their glory which is their ſhame is to be made manifeſt to all, that others may learn wiſdom by the fear of the Lord, which is to depart from evil.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A Coppy of another <hi>Letter</hi> from <hi>Thomas Atkin,</hi> with ſomething added in <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DAniel Baker,</hi> I this day had brought me by a Siſter of yours a large Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but little to any good purpoſe; you magnifie your ſelfe in your Gifts, as if no man have ſuch Knowledge as your ſelf; you may know much, but your Practiſe is far ſhort of what you ſeem to know; <hi>[Mark]</hi> you vilifie our Miniſters and Miniſtry, and call our Churches Maſs-houſes; your language and terms are provoking: Cannot you and them of your gang be quiet and exerciſe your Gifts in your own Meeting-places, but disturbe us in our Congregations, and Act in the Streets in a moſt uncivil manner, like diſtracted men then ſober perſons,<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <p>How if thou had been in the dayes of the holy Prophets <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> to have ſeen one go naked and bear a ſign three years, and another to bake his bread with mans dung or Cowes dung at the Commandement of the Lord, its like thou would not have ceaſed to falſly accuſe them to be diſtracted and uncivil perſons, mad-men, and the like.</p>
                        <p>But why ſhould the Spirit of the holy One be limited, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, or ſtopt (that made the body and every member of his Creature Man) from Commanding, or his Creature male or female from ſubjecting to their Lords Command in or by their body, without reſpect of the outward adorning Life; mens perſons, time, place, or dayes, that the Will of the Almighty Lord of Heaven and Earth might be done in it as it is in the new Heaven and in the new Earth, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the world might ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do Righteouſneſs, even as he is Holy and Righteous that calleth his people out of <hi>Babel,</hi> the Land of Darkneſs and Confuſion, leſt while they partake of her ſins they partake of her plagues and judgements; Lo the ſame voice cryes now in theſe latter dayes, He that hath an Ear to hear let him hear, and come forth, and turn to the Light thats low in the heart, freely from the Lord given to thee.</p>
                     </note> drawing Tumults about you to the diſturbance of our Peace; You and your Companions prophane the Lords Day, ſome opening their Shops on that day, which we can
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93715:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>no wayes allow of; you make a great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the Jaylor and his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; I doubt not but there is great Fault in all of them, there is no Good to be learned in ſuch places, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it is a Grief to all good People to ſee and hear ſuch Sins daily committed in ſuch places; and if it lieth upon your Spirit as you Write it doth, <hi>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his is falſe, I Writ not ſo, but I was burthened with the crying Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the City and Priſon, Lo in that fear and wiſdom of my Lord and Maſter, Chriſt the Light, I have cleared my Conſcience, whether thou and them who are the Cauſe of it hear or forbear.)</hi> I marvel you will ſtay ſo long in that place; If your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder Keeper bring you to my Houſe that I may talk with you, I may perhaps ſee Cauſe that you ſhall Return thither no more; when you are weary of your Company you may take my Advice, and ſo I leave you, Reſting</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your well-wiſhing Friend, <hi>THOMAS ATKIN.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <date>London, the <hi>24</hi> of Novemb.</date>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>After I had Written an Anſwer to the late Letter the <hi>25</hi> of the 9th. Month in the Morning, from the Lord had I freedom to paſs forth to <hi>Thomas Atkin</hi> with the Letter, and with the words of my Mouth to lay his wicked lyes and falſe and unjuſt Accuſations and Proceedings upon his own Head, and to warn him on the Lords behalf, who with his Servants are and will be clear of his Blood if he die in his Sins, with many more that reject the Truth, and perſecute the life of it, as its appearance is brought forth in, and by the Friends of Christ Jeſus the light of the World, that lighteth every man that cometh into the World.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>FRIEND,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>DId thou never read Chriſts words in the Scriptures of Truth, which ſaith, <hi>For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very idle word that men ſhall ſpeak they ſhall give Account in the day o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Judgement, and all Lyars ſhall have their part in the Lake that burns with Fire and Brimſtone;</hi> And how is it thou do not fear and tremble before the living God that hath given thee breath, but in the hardneſſe of thy heart and impenitency (inſtead of laying thy ſad wretched and miſerable eſtate to heart, when its ſo plainly laid before thee, had not the god of the World altogether blinded thine eye thou might ſee ſo much O man) who
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93715:9"/>yet fear not to heap up falſe Accuſations (againſt the Innocent) which thou and many more are truly guilty of, as I have ſufficiently proved to thee, who moſt wickedly and prophanely, ſaid to my Friend the Meſſenger this morning, That I had gathered all the Pick-pockets, and Whores, and Rogues in <hi>London</hi> about me; a wicked Lye; ſo I turn it back upon thy head, O man what will be thy end?</p>
                  <p>Art thou fit to bear the Name of a Ruler, a Chriſtian, a Magiſtrate, a Juſtice of Peace which ſhould be a terror to the Liar, the falſe Accuſer, the Evil-doer, and not fear the God of Truth thy ſelf, but ſpeak ſuch moſt wicked Lyes and falſe Accuſations, (to the ſhame of thy greedy dark Teachers) the Lord's witneſs in thy Conſcience, when the Lord viſits for all the Deeds done in thy body will bring them into remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and judge and condemne thee for the evil; and behold I yet call for thee to Repent and hearken to the witneſs in thee oppreſt, and ceaſe from thy wickedneſſe left thou die in thy ſins, who writ to me in thy late Letter after thou have undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly ſpoke contemptiouſly and vilely of me, and of what I writ in love to thy Soul.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſay I vilifie your Miniſters and Miniſtry; Thou err in ſaying ſo; for I do not vilifie them in ſpeaking the Truth of or concerning them, as thou may read and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by what I have written to thee; but can I ſpeak more vilely of them then thou in thy Letter to me, ſaying, <hi>There is no good to be learned in ſuch places, and thou doſt believe its a grief to all good people to ſee and hear ſuch ſins daily committed in ſuch places</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Priſons) to thy own ſhame thou have written this (better a milſtone were hanged about the neck of ſuch as offend Chriſts little ones by caſting them into ſuch places) and much more to the vilifying [as thou call it] of the hired Prieſts that take ſo much Quarterly gain (or yearly gain from their Quarter) to deceive the poor Priſoners who can learn no good here though they preach for Hire ſo often, ſo that thou have confirmed what I have truly written; and is it not time for them to be ſilent that are in deceit, in an evil way, how can they teach the good old way who are out of it themſelves; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this and Repent. Another Charge thou layſt to me, is for calling the Churches made with hands, Maſs-houſes; Did not the Popes adherents build them to ſay Maſſe in, and give them their Monks and Saints Names, as St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> St. <hi>Dunſton,</hi> St. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher,</hi> St. <hi>Katherin,</hi> St. <hi>Antlin,</hi> St. <hi>Rood,</hi> St. <hi>Giles,</hi> St. <hi>Clement, &amp;c.</hi> And how is it thou art ſo blind and dark, and called a Magiſtrate, and yet know not the Church of the living God, which is the pillar and ground of Truth, from an old Popiſh Maſſe-houſe made up of Lime and Stone with mens hands where God dwels not, and doſt not thou blaſpheme to call that a Church which is not, but I may ſay a figure of thy hard heart, who art yet a member of ſuch a Church which is not the body of Chriſt; See <hi>Col.</hi> 1.24. <hi>The true Church is the Body of Chriſt;</hi> but I deny with my life a ſtony Idols Temple (Steeple houſe, or Maſſe-houſe) that it is the Church or Body of Chriſt, or the pillar and ground of Truth which is the Church of the living God; behold thy blaſphemy and the damnable error of thy dark Teachers.</p>
                  <p>And why doſt thou continue heaping falſe Accuſations upon me and my dear friends the Lords Servants that Worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth, and deny the Pope and his Adherents Doctrines, heatheniſh Traditions. Cuſtoms, and vain Faſhions of the World that lieth in wickedneſs, the Lord will judge thee for theſe things; while thou have time Repent and prize it.</p>
                  <p>Thou tell me of my Friends <hi>Opening Shops on the Lords Day;</hi> but which day of the Week is not the Lords that made them. The Apoſtles Doctrine i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, One man eſteemeth one day above another, another eſteemeth every day alike; but what ſhall be done to ſuch? he doth not ſay, Away to Priſon with them, beat them, ſpoil their goods, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them, or we can no wayes allow of it, as thou ſay; Nay, but thus its written; <hi>Let every man be fully perſwaded in his own mind,</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5. Remember thou art
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93715:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſufficiently warned from this day forward (ſeeing the Lord hath given thee and many more a day of viſitation, of ſalvation, whether it be received or rejected) that thou have not a hand in perſecuting any for conſcience ſake, or for reproving ſin in the gate, in the Maſs-houſe or open ſtreet, leaſt the Lord with a quick and mighty ſtroak, as in a moment ſmite thee and take away the deſire of thine eyes, who art yet falſe accuſing me and my Friends, ſaying, <hi>Cannot you and them of your gang (with ſuch reproachfull and unſavoury words) be quiet,— but diſturb us in our Congregations, and act in the open ſtreets in a moſt uncivil manner, liker diſtracted men then ſober perſons, drawing tumults about you, to the diſturbance of our peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Know thou that if the King of darkneſſe, of Babylon, of Confuſion, did (or may) ſend greetings of peace (as in another caſe) to all that did or doth dwell in the earth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.25. yet the Prince of Life &amp; King of Righteouſneſs, Chriſt the Light of the World comes not to ſend peace on the Earth, but a Sword, ſee <hi>Luke</hi> 10.34, 35. and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel cries, <hi>wo, wo, wo to the Inhabitants of the Earth;</hi> Therefore think it not ſtrange that your peace is broken, or diſturbed, for no peace to wicked, but fear God, Repent and bring forth fruits meet for repentance unto life, leaſt thou die in thy ſins, for this is of truth that I write, whether thou hear or forbear,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From the Hole of the inner Priſon in the Poultry Counter,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>this</hi> 24 <hi>of the</hi> 9 <hi>mo.</hi> 1659.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>From thy Souls Friend that writes his name, <hi>Daniel Baker.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Here followeth a Coppy of a Letter ſent from a Friend of Gods Truth, to <hi>Thomas Allen</hi> Mayor of the City <hi>London.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THomas Allen;</hi> Ah Friend, what is this that thou haſt done in this thy proceeding againſt me, and to ſeparate me from my family where there is ſo much need of me, which thou little regardest, but exerciſeth cruelty on that day, the firſt day which thou calls the Sabbath or Lords day, even without mercy? Yet thou knows or ſhould know, that he or they that rule over men ſhould be just men, men of truth, ruling in the fear of God.</p>
                  <p>Friend, I was the laſt firſt day of the week ſave one in my ſhop in Gods fear, exercing my Conſcience void of offence towards God and man, doing no evil in word or deed to Man, Woman or Child; for my Religion which is Pure, is to keep unſpoted of the World, and ſo cannot joyn one with the World, in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving one day above another, but esteem every day alike, and am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in mine own mind, and know that the Kingdom of Heaven comes not with outward obſervation, and that to the Lord all dayes are alike good, and that it is the will of God our Sanctification to be Holy, as God is Holy, every day in all manner of converſation, to do Justly, to love Mercy, and to walk humbly with or before the Lord God who ſearcheth the Heart. And who have learned and are taught this by the Grace of God, which brings Salvation, which hath appeared unto all men, even to deny ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and to live Righteouſly, Soberly and Godly in this preſent World, to ſuch all daies are alike who are God-like; for the Lord God made every day good, and every Child of God that is born of God who is Light, walks in the Light, Chriſt the good day that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw and was glad, which is the true Reſt, which the Sabbath that was given to the <hi>Jewes</hi> for a Sign, was a ſhadow of; even of the Subſtance,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93715:10"/>Chriſt the Light, the good day of God, the reſt; which remaines, in whom all the Shadows, Signes, and dayes end. And who now are rooted in him, and built up in him, Christ the Light, and walk in the Light (which through believing in are become Children of) and are joyned and united to the Body, Chriſt the ſubſtance that ends the ſhadows, they dwelling in God who is light, are freed from the begarly Rudiments, and cannot be in any wiſe brought into bondage to them again to obſerve days, or esteem one day above another; and they now whoſe life is in obſerving of dayes, which were appointed &amp; given as ſhadows and ſigns of the ſubſtance their life is not yet in the ſubſtance Chriſt the Light, but in the Signs &amp; ſhadows, and ſo as yet know not Chriſt the Light manifeſt in their fleſh, to redeem out of the bondage of corruption, but ſtill remain children of the Bond-woman, under the bondage of ſin an Satan, and ſo are not holy any day of the week, and then, cannot keep or walk holily on the first day of the week, or on any day elſe.</p>
                  <p>But prethee conſider, if thou have a Law for what thou doth againſt me, and wouldeſt have me and all men account thee a just man, as thou ought to be (and art called a Juſtice) for I and all men may judge of thee to be a Juſtice, and a just man, if thou do juſtice impartially without reſpect of perſons; Now, how haſt thou ſo dealt with me to ſend me to priſon for opening my win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and becauſe I will not ſhut them at the Marſhal thy ſervants pleaſure, I being a Free man of the City in equity ought to have as much freedom in opening my windows and to keep them open, as thou to command thy Servant and horſes to labour on the firſt day of the week; therefore if thou wilt do juſtice without partiality, command the Marſhal thy ſervant to carry thee to Priſon, and if thou be not willing to go ſo, at his word, in the Name of the Keepers of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of England, if the Marſhals ſervant thruſt thee violently out of thy doors as he did me, why let it be ſo; and if another of his ſervants take hold on thee, and kick thee very wickedly and violently as he did me, why, bear it; and if he take thee by the Collar of thy doublet and band on both ſides thy neck, and ſhake thee as a Dog would worry a Sheep, as one of the Marſhals Servants did me, and the other carrying a ſtick under my back, lifted it up quick on purpoſe to have me fall on it to hurt me, let him do ſo to thee and bear it, and when they have halled thee and dragged thee to the Poultry Counter gate, if the Marſhals Servant ſearch and rifle thy pockets, and take what he will out, and give thee what he will again as he did by me, the Marſhal standing by, and then thruſt thee into a ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l betwixt the doors of the Priſon, why, be content; and ſpeak Truth, and thou may ſay, I in commanding my Servants and Horſes to work, am as great a Tranſgreſsor and offender, as be that open his Shop Windows (if it be a tranſgreſſior) and was thus dealt withal; and thou may ſay I ſhall not mend my behaviour in commanding my man and horſes not to work on the firſt day of the week, being one of the ſix on which God commanded men ſhould labour;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93715:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>And then thou may ſay, if I be kept there in the hole of the Priſon, till I have learned to do justice without reſpect of Perſons, I deſervedly ſuffer. But this man committed to Priſon from Tower street, was badly dealt withal and cruelly perſecuted by reaſon of my order, when I ſhould have been a terror to evil doers that harmed him, and I have not yet learned to do justice without reſpect of perſons:</p>
                  <p>Friend, let it ſink down into thee, the ſence of this thy unjuſt dealing with me and repent. And ſend me word what thou intendeſt to do with me, and conſider if thou would in thy will ſend me to priſon, whether thou ought not to have ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified under thy hand in writing the Crime thou layeſt againſt me; in ſuch a matter Noble Festus, the Profeſsors call a heathen, will condemn thee, ſee Acts. <hi>25.</hi> for this day I asked (the Turn-key) for a copy of the Mittimus by which I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Priſon, and his anſwer was, there is none, though now it be about ten dayes ſince I was caſt into Priſon. Now conſider if it be not a thing unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſend a priſoner, and not to ſignifie to the Priſoner and goaler the Crimes laid against him. And if thou art an unreaſonable man, what juſtice can any expect from thee, if thou art a reaſonable man, diſcover it hereafter before all men, in doing justly, loving mercy, and walking humbly before the Lord God; if thou go onto perſecute the Innocent, I know it will be bitterneſſe in the latter end.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>From the Lords Priſoner for the teſtimony of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in denying the Sign, and witneſſing the ſubſtance, A Friend to thy pretious ſoul but an enemy to injuſtice and perſecution,</hi> Humphrey Bache.</signed>
                     <dateline>The Inner Priſon called the Hole in the Poultry Counter, <date>the <hi>29th</hi> of the <hi>9</hi> month, <hi>1659.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Conſider whether or no thou provide for my Children and Family, who have not a Wife to look to them in my abſence, who caſt me into Priſon for working on that day which thou make thy Horſes work, is not this partiallity and contrary to the Law of God, that the Creatures ſhould work that day that man ſhould not work; but ſurely if you did take as much care for the Poor, and Beggars, and Children, and Fatherleſs, and Widows, and Criples at your Steeple-houſe Doors, and Alleys, and Corners of Streets; your Women with Two or Three Children in their Lapps crying for Bread, thou would not turn the Sword againſt me as thou doſt, but relieve them and ſee that they were relieved, for it is a grief to hear ſuch a Cry in your Streets, beſides Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, Oaths in Taverns and Alehouſes, Tipling-houſes, Priſons and places of pleaſure, Bouls, Playes, ſhews, the vanities thats acted and done in the City under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here, which makes the ſtreets even to ſtink again, to loath and Surfeit and defile Nature, for the ſhameleſs, unlearned, untaught, unſavoury carriages among peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93715:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>are we moved of the Lord God, at the Command of Chriſt Jeſus the Righteouſneſs of God to cry Repentance among you, to go in Sackcloth and Aſhes among you, and to go naked among you, a figure of your nakedneſs of the garments of Righteouſneſs, which ſhould be a praiſe in your ſtreets, and to cry againſt your Idolatrous Worſhip, the preaches for money by the Hour-glaſſe, who have not profited the people at all, but ſuch as teachers for filthy lucre and bear Rule by their means, and Divine for money and teaches for the fleece, that ſeeketh their gain from their Quarter, greedy dumb Doggs that can never have enough, are ſuch as fit this people.</p>
            <p>Now if people bid a Drunkard he ſhould not be drunk, a Swearer he ſhould not ſwear, a Lyar he ſhould not lye, we are called peace-breakers, and priſoned by you; Oh! the Righteous ſuffer and are grieved to ſee ſo much Feaſting and Superfluity of all things in abundance among you, and yet let your brethren and fellow-members lie cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up and down ſtreets for bread, and have no compaſſion or bowels of mercy.</p>
            <p>And your Shows and your Playes of all ſorts, and call people together with Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets to it, this now is not called as Evil among you; but if a man go and warn ſinners to Repentance, he ſhall be caſt into priſon; ſo he that reproves evil in the gate is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a prey among you; you that ſay the Scripture is your Rule, the Apoſtle ſaith you ſhould not judge one another about dayes, one man did obſerve a day, another did not, the Apoſtles judgement was, <hi>Let every man be fully perſwaded in his own mind;</hi> and why could not you be ſatisfied ſeeing I am fully perſwaded in my own mind, but if you make an Idol of a day, God will abhor you.</p>
            <p>Since I was freed out of priſon, <hi>Thomas Atkin</hi> with bitter enmity met me in the ſtreet, and he drew near, and ſaid, That we were a burthen to all places where we come; And I anſwered, That we were a burthen to wicked Magiſtrates and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe where we come; and I ſay we know its written, <hi>The burthen of the Word of the Lord for Iſrael [ſaith the Lord] which ſtretcheth forth the Heavens, and layeth the foundation of the Earth, and formeth the Spirit of man within him,</hi> (mark that.)</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Behold I will make</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>a Cup of trembling unto all the People round about, when they ſhall be in the Siege both againſt</hi> Judah <hi>and againſt</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and in that day will I make</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem <hi>a burthenſome Stone for all people, all that burthen themſelves with it ſhall be cut i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in pieces though all the people upon the Earth be gathered together againſt it,</hi>
               </q>
               <bibl>Zach. 12.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93715:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93715:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:93715:13"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93715:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93715:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93715:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:93715:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93715:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93715:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93715:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93715:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93715:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93715:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93715:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93715:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:93715:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93715:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93715:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93715:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93715:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93715:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
